A Guide to the Cocke and related families Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #2433-ab
Cocke and related families Papers 1858-1879
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
2433-ab
12 items
John Page Elliott
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This material was given to the Library by John Page Elliott of Charlottesville, Virginia, on April 22, 1991.
Scope and Content
These twelve letters, 1858-1879, and n.d., pertain chiefly to the family and estate of Philip St. George Cocke. Topics of interest include Belmead, the Civil War, and the University of Virginia. Typed transcripts are available for the majority of these letters.
Container List
- Sallie Browne Cocke to John Bowdoin Cocke, Edinburgh, Scotland, 1858 July 26
  concerning family news
- Daniel Coleman, Army of the Mississippi, to John Bowdoin Cocke, 1862 April 14
  relating news of a great battle near Corinth[presumably Shiloh] and the condition of the troops
- "Aunt F.," South Isle, Charlotte, North Carolina, to Charles Hartwell Cocke, 1863 July 20
  mentioning the fall of Vicksburg, news of killed and wounded, and thoughts on the war
- Major Robert B. Taylor, Bremo Recess, to John Bowdoin Cocke, 1863 Sep 30
  expressing gratitude and requesting a loan
- William G. Strange, Dunlora, to John Bowdoin Cocke, at the request of Major William S. Dabney, 1863 Oct 10
  inquiring about Major Douthat's property in Powhatan which is advertised for sale
- William Ruffin Coleman Cocke, University of Virginia, to John Bowdoin Cocke, 1866 Jan 7
  concerning financial and management burdens of Belmead. He comments on the need of a "reliable labour-system" and the "abundant evidences that the negro will not furnish the desideratum."
- William H. Richardson, Jr. to Major John Bowdoin Cocke, 1866 Dec 17
  commenting on Cocke's marriage and the reconstruction of the South
- William West Gilmer, Ivy Creek, to Dr. Cary Charles Cocke, 1867 Feb 22
  mentioning Thad[deus Steven]'s bill, apparently concerning the division of land belonging to southern plantation owners among the freedmen, refers to a conversation with his former "slave Ralph now Wormley" concerning voting, and tobacco crop prices. He mentions University of Virginia professors J[ohn] B[arbee] Minor, J[ames] L[awrence] Cabell, and [John] Staige Davis.
- Samuel M. Wilson, Norfolk, Virginia, to John Bowdoin Cocke, Belmead, 1871 July 5
  concerning financial matters
- John Bowdoin Cocke, Belmead, to Cary Charles Cocke, 1876 Jan 31
  re getting tobacco to market and family news
- William Ruffin Coleman Cocke, Richmond, to John Bowdoin Cocke, West View, Goochland County, Virginia, 1879 May 16
  concerning a new plan for Belmead
- Incomplete letter, n.d.
  concerning Belmead and sending Lucy [Cocke] for her education